<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian mans assuring house. And a sinners conuersion Two sermons; the former, preached, before the Prince his Highnesse at St. Iames: the other to his Maiesties houshold at White-hall, on Sunday the 6. of February by George Meriton Doctor of Diuinitie, and Deane of Peterborough.</title>
            <author>Meriton, George, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17837</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112663</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847909</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07450)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1354:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian mans assuring house. And a sinners conuersion Two sermons; the former, preached, before the Prince his Highnesse at St. Iames: the other to his Maiesties houshold at White-hall, on Sunday the 6. of February by George Meriton Doctor of Diuinitie, and Deane of Peterborough.</title>
                  <author>Meriton, George, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 53, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for Ralfe Mab, and are to be sold in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Greyhound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12976:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12976:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIAN MANS ASSVRING HOUSE. AND A SINNERS Conuerſion. TWO SERMONS; The former, preached, before the <hi>Prince</hi> his Highneſſe at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames:</hi> The other to his Maieſties Houſhold at
<hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> on Sunday the 6. of February</p>
            <p>By GEORGE MERITON Doctor of <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> and Deane of
<hi>Peterborough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>Ralfe Mab,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Paules Churchyard</hi> at the ſigne of the
<hi>Greyhound.</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12976:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12976:2"/>
            <head>TO THE PRINCE HIS MOST excellent Highneſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt noble Prince.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſed your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to heare this Sermon with patience, and afterwards to command it at my hands: which I offer vnto you (as Dauids ſeruants did their gifts for the Temple)<note place="margin">1. Chron.
19.9.</note> with a good heart wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. It is an incomparable comfort
<pb facs="tcp:12976:3"/>to all true profeſſors (in the number of whom J deſire to be accounted) that your Grace at theſe yeares is ſo religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſpoſed. The God of mercy fill you more and more with his bleſsings, that it may bee ſaid of Prince <hi>CHARLES,</hi> as was ſpoken of our greatest Maſter Chriſt, (<hi>And the child increaſed in wiſdome and ſtature and in fauour with God and man.</hi>)<note place="margin">Luk.
2.52.</note>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By him that ſerueth your Highneſſe with his earneſt praier to God for your happineſſe, <hi>George Meriton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12976:3"/>
            <head>THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2. PETER 1.10.</bibl>
                  <p>Wherefore Brethren the rather giue diligence to make your Calling and Election ſure.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE office of a Miniſter (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of three ſpeciall duties: <hi>tingere, offerre, docere.</hi> And anſwerable vnto theſe, are there as many places appointed in the Church for his attendance: the <hi>Fonte,</hi> the
<hi>Altar,</hi> the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> The <hi>Font</hi> for dipping or bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing; the <hi>Altar</hi> for offering: the <hi>Pulpit</hi> for tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. In Chriſts commiſſion (<hi>Goe teach all Nations, baptizing them &amp;c.</hi>)<note place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> Teaching, hath the firſt place. And as it is chiefeſt in commiſſion, ſo among all points of Diuinitie, that can be taught, there is no <hi>One</hi> of greater moment, than to bee acquainted with the counſell of God, concerning our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12976:4"/> What can be more comfortable, than Pauls (<hi>Certus ſum</hi>)<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> I am well aſſured? what ſweeter newes, than to heare that <hi>it is our Fathers pleaſure to giue vs a kingdome?</hi> what more acceptable, than to know that <hi>wee are the choſen of God?</hi> Choſen (infallibly) to be ſaued? Tranſlated from death to life? Neuer to bee ſnatched out of the hands of Chriſt? This high point of Religion, ſo comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, ſo ſweet, ſo acceptable, I am now about to deliuer. My text craueth your diligence, not only in the reading: but much more your beſt inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, in labouring for the ſame. (<hi>Giue rather dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> (<hi>Brethren</hi>) <hi>to make your calling and election ſure.</hi>) It is S. Peters aduiſe, to the diſperſed Iewes, who were now become Chriſtians and had obteined like pretious faith with others.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.1.</note> The words haue dependance (<hi>wherefore</hi>) and the Context is this: In the verſes before, he exhorteth them to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of excellent vertues, which would adorne their profeſſion: as,
<hi>Knowledge, Temperance, Patience, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, Brotherly kindneſſe, Charitie,</hi> and ſuch like:<note place="margin">verſ. 5.6.7.</note> if theſe (ſaith he) abound in you, you ſhall neither be idle, nor vnfruitfull, nor blind, as men which cannot ſee, or (at leaſt) not remember that they are purged from their ſinnes.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 8.9.</note> To be (<hi>idle</hi>) <hi>nihil agentes,</hi> doing nothing, is the root of euill: To be (<hi>vnfruitfull</hi>) <hi>aliud agentes,</hi> doing things impertinent, is the note of folly: To be (<hi>blind and in darkneſſe</hi>)
<hi>male agentes,</hi> committing wickedneſſe, is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of miſchiefe. He that ſtandeth, let him take heed that he doth not fall. Brethren, you haue not thus learned Chriſt: ſuch cariage befits not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerts:<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12976:4"/>
               <hi>wherefore the</hi> (<hi>rather</hi>) <hi>giue diligence, to make your calling and election ſure. H&amp;c nobis apponuntur, nobis proponuntur,</hi> (ſaith S. Bernard) theſe things are written for our learning. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Peters good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell hath been reiected by the Iewes, and they are fallen; the deſtruction of them ſhould be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to vs. Wherefore ſuppoſe (I pray you) that our Apoſtle were now turning himſelfe vnto the Gentiles, and were (<hi>thus</hi>) ſpeaking to you: Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren it is enough, that hitherto you haue miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent the time: ſome in (<hi>idleneſſe</hi>) ſhorting in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer like ſonnes of confuſion:<note place="margin">Prou. 10.</note> ſome in (<hi>vanities</hi>) which is the trauell of fooles:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.</note> ſome in (<hi>ſinne</hi>) which is the ſeruice of the Deuill. It is enough, that you haue wearied your bodies, troubled your wits, broken your ſleepes, in the purſuit of the world: ſome ſetting nets for <hi>commodities,</hi> as the
<hi>Spider</hi> doth his web to catch a <hi>Flye:</hi> ſome ſtriuing for honours, ſtill building vpwards, as if <hi>Nimrods Tower</hi> were now too low: ſome wallowing in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, as if they would lye deeper and longer with the ſwine in the mire. My brethren, what profit can be in thoſe things, whereof ye are, or may be, or ſhall be aſhamed? The Iewes are fallen, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe you (<hi>Gentiles</hi>) firſt ſeeke the kingdome of God.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Giue diligence rather to make your calling and election ſure.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The parts of the Text are two:
<list>
                  <item> 1. <hi>A motiue.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 2. <hi>A dutie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:12976:5"/>
                  <item> The <hi>Motiue,</hi> in this word (<hi>Brethren.</hi>)</item>
                  <item> The <hi>Dutie</hi> in the reſt: And firſt of the
<hi>Motiue</hi> (<hi>Brethren.</hi>)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>There are Brethren by
<list>
                  <item> 1 <hi>Humanitie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 2 <hi>Country.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 3 <hi>Affinitie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 4 <hi>Conſanguinitie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 5 <hi>Chriſtianitie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item> 1 For the firſt: <hi>God will require the life of a man at the hands of his brother.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 9.5.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item> 2 For the ſecond: <hi>Paul deſireth to be ſeparate from Chriſt for the Iſraelites his brethren.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom.
9.3.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item> 3 For the third: <hi>Abraham ſaid to Lot his nephew, Let there be no ſtrife between me and thee, for we are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen.
13.8.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item> 4 For the fourth: <hi>Children of the whole or halfe parents, as Iacob and Eſau, Andrew and Peter, the</hi> 12. <hi>Patriarkes were Brethren.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 5 For the fift: <hi>One is your maſter (Christ) and all ye are Brethren.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 23.8.</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Brother is a name of much loue, and it mooueth howſoeuer it be taken. One (<hi>Man</hi>) is not borne a <hi>wolfe</hi> vnto another, but ſo made by <hi>cuſtome:</hi> though we are diſperſed vpon the face of the earth, yet are we framed out of the ſame moulde. (The <hi>ſlime</hi> of the earth is our common <hi>Mother</hi>) wee are formed with the ſame ſtampe. (A <hi>reaſonable ſoule</hi> is our common <hi>character</hi>) we haue one Authour from whence wee all come (<hi>God</hi> who is our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<hi>Father.</hi>) <hi>Non taliter fecit omni Creatura.</hi> It is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12976:5"/>not ſo with the foules of the aire, the beaſts of the field, the fiſhes of the ſea. Only one <hi>Man</hi> was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, from whom all ſhould proceed, that a ſtrength of <hi>Brotherhood</hi> might be amongſt all. And if S. Peter had been pleaſed, to haue preſſed the word (<hi>Brethren</hi>) in this large ſenſe, and had aduiſed the Iewes, euen by their common humanitie, <hi>to make their calling and election ſure:</hi> his motiue were not to be deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>Our (<hi>Country</hi>) wherein we haue our <hi>being</hi> and
<hi>breathing,</hi> which ſuſteineth, feedeth, miniſtreth content vnto vs: wherein we worſhip one God, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey one King: where our ſtocke and linage doth remaine: and where are many monuments of our ancient predeceſſors:
<hi>omnes in ſe charitates complexa eſt</hi> (ſaith the Orator) hath ſuch ſtrong motiues to affect vs, as <hi>Vliſſes</hi> is reported (in
<hi>Homer</hi>) to preferre the ſmoake of his country before the immortalitie of the gods. Yf then our Apoſtle had ſaid in plain termes, (<hi>Countrymen</hi>) I exhort you, euen by the name of (<hi>Iewry</hi>) our promiſed land, where you haue once pleaſantly liued, and wherin our father
<hi>Abraham</hi> and his poſteritie lie buried: by all the ſweetneſſe that our Country hath afforded you, I exhort you, <hi>to make your calling and election ſure;</hi> the ſtrength of his motiue, were already much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed.</p>
            <p>(<hi>Kindred</hi>) is yet a further and faſter <hi>bonde,</hi> and ſo reputed both by the law of God and man; the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name whereof poſſeſſeth many with ſo gratefull delight, as that they are ready to claime it of thoſe, who are many degrees remoued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12976:6"/>(<hi>Naturall Brotherhood</hi>) goeth beyond the reſt, in ſo much as nothing is deemed more <hi>odious,</hi> then that thoſe who are <hi>conioyned</hi> in <hi>bloud,</hi> ſhould be
<hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned</hi> in <hi>affection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the names of (<hi>Affinitie</hi> and
<hi>conſanguinitie</hi>) haue abilitie and force to plead, moſt of all (<hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie</hi>) which bindeth men together in the ſtraigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<hi>coniunction,</hi> hauing one <hi>God</hi> for our <hi>Father:</hi> one
<hi>Church</hi> for our <hi>Mother:</hi> one <hi>Chriſt</hi> for our elder
<hi>Brother:</hi> being all begotten by the ſame <hi>immortall ſeed, waſhed</hi> by the lauar of one <hi>new birth, congluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> by the ſinnowes of the ſame <hi>faith: nouriſhed</hi> by the <hi>milke</hi> of the ſame <hi>word:</hi> hauing all the ſame <hi>hope</hi> of
<hi>immortalitie</hi> in the <hi>world to come.</hi> The name of this (<hi>Brotherhood</hi>) is (ſaith S. <hi>Baſil</hi>) like a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious oyntment, which ſweetneth by a pleaſing perfume the whole Church of God, and by ſo much is it the more forcible, by how much <hi>Grace</hi> is a ſtronger bonde then (<hi>Nature.</hi>) That of (<hi>Nature</hi>) repreſenteth the ſimilitude of <hi>bodies:</hi> but this of (<hi>Grace</hi>) the agreement of mindes. And hence it commeth that there is no paſſionate louer will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure more for his beſt Beloued, than one true Chriſtian brother will aduenture for another. A <hi>Louer</hi> (as they ſay) is tried by theſe three things: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, hee will vndergoe any labour for his loues good (ſo did <hi>Hercules</hi> for the loue of <hi>Omphale.</hi>) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, he will ſuſteine hard meaſure offred him for her cauſe (ſo did <hi>Iacob</hi> for the loue of
<hi>Rachel.</hi>) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, hee will abide, whatſoeuer ſhee pleaſe to impoſe vpon him (ſo did <hi>Sampſon</hi> for the loue of
<hi>Dalilah.</hi>) And ſuch are the <hi>affections</hi> of
<hi>Chriſtians</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:12976:6"/>one to another. They are content to ſuffer, <hi>pro fratribus, à fratribus, propter fratres;</hi> They will <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,</hi> for their <hi>good: Beare,</hi> for their <hi>ſakes: put vp,</hi> at <hi>their hands.</hi> And why will they doe this, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are <hi>Brethren?</hi> If then <hi>Nature</hi> be able to mooue, much more grace: If our <hi>Country,</hi> much more our
<hi>Religion:</hi> If <hi>affinitie,</hi> much more the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of
<hi>Gods ſpirit:</hi> If the name of <hi>Brother,</hi> in euery ſenſe bee forceable, then out of doubt in a <hi>Chriſtian ſignification</hi> it is exceeding ſtrong. Heere is then the wiſdome of our Apoſtle <hi>S. Peter,</hi> who to perſwade a matter of maine importance, is not content to expreſſe his affection, in a <hi>vulgar terme;</hi> he calleth vpon the Iewes, not by the name of <hi>Men,</hi> of <hi>Kinſmen,</hi> of
<hi>Countrymen, &amp;c.</hi> but as if ſuch words had been but tokens of an
<hi>eſtraunged minde,</hi> he tells them of their <hi>adoption</hi> which they had in <hi>Christ:</hi> calls to their mindes that <hi>inviolable knot</hi> of <hi>loue,</hi> wherewith all of them, as members (by the
<hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Loue</hi>) were ioyned vnto <hi>Chriſt</hi> their
<hi>head.</hi> And the rather to preuaile, he <hi>ſaluteth</hi> them by the name of <hi>Brethren</hi> in the ſweeteſt (that is in the
<hi>Chriſtian</hi>) <hi>ſenſe. Wherefore my Brethren.</hi> This is likewiſe the practiſe of S. Paul (<hi>I beſeech you Brethren.</hi>)<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> And in his Epiſtle to Philemon (<hi>Brother refreſh my bowels.</hi>)<note place="margin">2. verſ. Phile.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe Apoſtles beloued (me thinks) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a
<hi>method</hi> vnto <hi>Ministers</hi> of a louing behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our towards the flocke of Chriſt. It is fit (I confes) ſometimes to vſe ſharpe reprehenſion, to fling fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands, to denounce iudgments: where ſinne is red and ranke (<hi>Bonarges</hi>) a ſonne of <hi>Thunder</hi> is more requiſite then (<hi>Barnabas</hi>) the ſon of <hi>conſolation:</hi> yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12976:7"/>
               <hi>ſuſpendite verbera, producite vbera</hi> (ſaith S.
<hi>Bernard</hi>) hearers may not be commonly gauled or goared. It is a point of high skill to catch a ſoule by craft.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul.</hi>) Brethren if a man be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by any ſinne (reſtore him) or as the word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth put him into ioint. Bones out of ioint muſt not be boiſterouſlie touched: That Surgion deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth praiſe who lightly preſſeth the wound, and handleth it <hi>cleuerlie,</hi> with the tops of his fingers: not he that rudely thruſteth in his fiſt. Manna is pleaſant vnto many, which cannot patiently abide the rod of <hi>Aaron:</hi> Mildneſſe hath bent where ſeuerity could not breake: The horſeleach by gentle ſucking draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more bloud, then the Gnat doth by her fierce biting. He that will cleanſe a glaſſe muſt not rub it too hard, leaſt in laboring to cleanſe it, he breaketh it in pieces. Such as ſeek to perſwade by ſharpneſſe, <hi>Quos volunt correctiores faciunt plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> deteriores</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) they cleanſe not, but breake the glaſſe: they pinche, but they draw no bloud: there actions without skill, comes oftimes to ends with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out profit. Away then with rough and boiſterous cariage: though thou wert as good, and as great as S.
<hi>Peter,</hi> yet it beſt beſeemeth thee to ſupport with mildneſſe: to ſtrengthen with gentleneſſe: to inſtruct with meekneſſe: to imitate <hi>S. Peter,</hi> who carrieth Balme in his mouth, ſauoureth of the ſweeteſt oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and ſtricking out the teeth of his words (leaſt in biting the Iewes hee might chance to grieue them) to expreſſe his loue, and winne them to his purpoſe he calls them (<hi>Brethren</hi>) wherefore brethren (thus much of the motiue) now to the duty.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:12976:7"/>
               <hi>Giue diligence rather to make your Calling and Election ſure.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Euerie dutie muſt be known, and done. Firſt we muſt know it, then doe it: God willeth his people firſt to teach their children the law (there is to know it) and then to ſee them keep it (there is to doe it.)
<hi>Theſe two words in my Text</hi> (calling and Election) <hi>ſtand for inſtruction to informe; the other ſerue for action to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> Calling hath precedency, not becauſe it is firſt in Gods counſaile, but for that it hath priority in mans conceiuing. The former being (indeed) the execution of the latter. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> order of ſtanding in the Text, preſcribes vnto vs a rule of ſearching: firſt to look to our calling then to our Election. Calling (to begin as the Text doth guide me) is a worke of God in Chriſt by the Spirit, whereby we are tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from darkneſſe to light: from nature to grace: from the kingdome of Sathan, to the Church of God. The abſolute Lord of all creatures is God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and therefore hath he power, to call into his owne kingdome both when and whom he will. <hi>It is God alone that calleth the things that are not, as though they were</hi> (as S.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh.)<note place="margin">Rom. 4.17.</note> And albeit thoſe are ſaid to be called, who any waies do anſwer their calling, or yeeld obedience thereunto: (wherof ſome doe it in externall profeſſion, ſome in heart, ſome in both) yet is calling firſt of all and principally directed to ſuch as are elect. It pertaineth to others as mixed in their ſociety. And hence ariſeth a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of calling. Sometimes it is operatiue, when <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12976:8"/>God worketh his will as well as reueales it. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times only ſignificatiue, when God opens his mind vnto men, but for iuſt cauſes beſt known to himſelfe, ſpareth to work it in them. In the calling of God which is operatiue and effectuall, there is a double act:
<hi>Inuitation</hi> and <hi>admisſion.</hi> Inuitement is, when God offereth eternall life, outwardly by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell, and inwardly by the inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heauenly deſires. Admiſſion is, when we are actually remoued from nature to grace: taken out of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and by faith ingrafted into Chriſt the ſecond: for hereby are we made the reall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the kingdome of God: And this is that <hi>calling</hi> which we are to make ſure.</p>
            <p>Election is a decree of God, in which according to the good pleaſure of his will, he hath choſen ſome, to euerlaſting life in Chriſt their Sauiour. Firſt (Iſay) it is Gods decree: for there is nothing in the world, which commeth to paſſe either in the whole or in the parts, without the eternall and vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able decree of God. And therefore whereas ſome are actually ſaued, others reiected, it is not for that their lucke and fortune was better, but becauſe God before all worlds did purpoſe and ordaine the ſame. Secondly, this decree is according to the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his will, for the impulſiue cauſe which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him thereunto, was not the foreſight of faith and good works (for theſe are the fruits of Gods ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) <hi>He hath choſen vs that we might be holy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> but his loue: his will: his good pleaſure. <hi>We are predeſtinate according to the good pleaſure of God</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>)<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.5.</note> And where as man firſt chooſeth, then loueth, according<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12976:8"/>to that of the Poet. <hi>Primum quod amare velis, reperire labora;</hi> it is otherwiſe with God, who firſt loueth, then electeth. <hi>He will haue mercy on whom he will haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> Firſt there is his will, then followes mercie: Thirdly his choice is but of ſome to euerlaſting life: The number of the elect in the iudgement of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is great, euen all that are called; for our Apoſtle ſpeaking to all the Iewes which were called, bids them make your <hi>election ſure:</hi> The number of the elect in the iudgement of verity, is ſmall; <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi> Conſider them in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and they are innumerable:
<hi>Mundum redemit de mundo</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>he hath redeemed a world out of the world:</hi> conſider them with others and they are but a handfull euen as gleanings after a harueſt (as the Prophet ſpeaketh.) <hi>All men are by nature the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 15.19.</note> Out of theſe hath God choſen ſome: he that taketh all cannot be ſaid to chooſe. And therefore ſauing grace is no vniuerſall reſpect, vnleſſe we make the ſtreame more large than the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. Fourthly, his choice is in Chriſt our Sauiour.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> The foundation of Gods election is Chriſt Ieſus alone. We are choſen to ſaluation (not for Chriſt) but in Chriſt. As he is God, we are choſen of him: as he is mediator we are choſen in him. And this is our election which we muſt make ſure. We know the matter of our dutie, let vs goe on to practiſe: And for our better proceeding, there are foure queſtions to be diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12976:9"/>Queſtions
<list>
                  <item> 1 <hi>Why:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 2 <hi>Whether:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 3 <hi>What:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item> 4 <hi>How:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Why.</hi>
               </note>Why ſhould we be diligent to make our <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Election</hi> ſure? Are they not ſure of themſelues? Are not thoſe who are indeed called and choſen, without faile to attaine <hi>Euerlaſting life? Paul</hi> takes it for a
<hi>Concluſion,</hi> that the purpoſe of God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to
<hi>Election</hi> muſt remaine ſure,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.11.</note> and that the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of God is without repentance:<note place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>I am</hi> (ſaith God)<note place="margin">Exod. 3.</note> not <hi>will be.</hi> For <hi>Nouitas initium teſtificatur, I am;</hi> not <hi>hath beene;</hi> for <hi>Vetuſtas finem comminatur</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>I am: neither will be: nor hath beene,</hi> but (as S. <hi>Austin</hi> ſayth) <hi>Aeterna veritas &amp; vera aternitas, an eternall truth and a true eternity.</hi> Now as the
<hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of God is immutable, ſo are his wils and
<hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi> The ſtrength of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is not as
<hi>Man</hi> that hee ſhould repent:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> hee altreth not by <hi>Conſent,</hi> and who hath reſiſted his will (ſayth S. <hi>Paul.</hi>)<note place="margin">Rom. 9.19.</note> Hee changeth not by
<hi>Constraint,</hi> why ſhould wee then make our <hi>Calling</hi> and
<hi>Election</hi> ſure? <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> haue a double
<hi>conſideration: as they are in God, as they are in Man.</hi> In God,
<hi>they are ſure; In Man;</hi> they muſt be made ſure. I know my Sheepe (ſayth Chriſt)<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.14.</note> there is
<hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Election</hi> in reſpect of God. Thus are they ſure (And I am knowen of <hi>mine</hi>) <hi>Heere is Calling</hi> and
<hi>Election</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Man,</hi> thus are they <hi>made ſure.</hi> They muſt then be made ſure, not in Gods <hi>counſell,</hi> but in mans <hi>conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Whether.</hi>
               </note>But can this
<hi>aſſuranre</hi> be made? The indiſpoſition of our <hi>Nature</hi> is ſuch, our hidden and and ſecret <hi>ſins</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12976:9"/>ſo many: as a man would thinke, there ſhould euer remaine a <hi>ſcruple</hi> in the <hi>Soule.</hi> Yet it is confeſſed at all hands: (<hi>The Church of Rome denieth</hi> it not) but that <hi>aſſurance</hi> may be made. It were in vaine for S. <hi>Peter</hi> to exhort vs to giue <hi>diligence</hi> to
<hi>make them ſure,</hi> if they could not be <hi>aſſured.</hi> Proue your <hi>ſelue,</hi> (ſayth S. <hi>Paul</hi>)<note place="margin">2. Cor.
13.</note> 
               <hi>whether</hi> you bee in the faith or not. Hee takes it for granted, that hee that hath faith, may know he hath it: and therefore by conſequent, that he may be aſſured of his <hi>Calling</hi> and
<hi>Election:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a ſauing <hi>faith</hi> is an vndoubted marke of both. <hi>Reioyce</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) to his <hi>Diſciples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>that your names are written in heauen.</hi> To reioice in things vnknown: we cannor: to ioy our ſelues in things
<hi>vncertaine,</hi> is but an <hi>induction</hi> of griefe: Doubtfull
<hi>preſumptions,</hi> proue <hi>certaine confuſions.</hi> We may aſſure our ſelues then, that they may be <hi>aſſured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>What.</hi>
               </note>I but what kind of
<hi>Aſſurance</hi> are we to ſeeke after? heere ſtands the
<hi>diffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence</hi> betwixt
<hi>Rome</hi> and vs, for howſoeuer we cannot looke for ſuch a one (but that which ſometimes may bee ioyned with doubting) eſpecially when temptations ſhall lay hold vpon vs: yet (ſay they) it is to be had by extraordinary Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: we, by ordinary meanes. <hi>They ſay:</hi> that it can be but probable. <hi>We,</hi> that it may be infallible. <hi>Theirs</hi> commeth from <hi>hope:</hi> which maketh but <hi>Goniecture. Ours</hi> from
<hi>faith:</hi> which giueth a <hi>Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. They maintaine certitude</hi> in reſpect of obiect one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that is of the thing beleeued: <hi>We,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect</hi> alſo: that is of the party beleeuing.
<hi>The</hi> one ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of the Immutability of that, which cannot be otherwiſe then it is, the <hi>other</hi> from the meanes,<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12976:10"/>wherby it is perſwaded vnto vs. They find it in ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable feelings which are oftimes <hi>deceiptfull: We,</hi> hold it by way of pledge, &amp; as an erneſt in a bargain, which putteth all out of queſtion.<note place="margin">2 Cor 1.22.</note> They tell this vs, is <hi>arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy:</hi> we with S. <hi>Austin</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Auſtin de verbis D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>m. ſerm.</hi> 28.</note> ſay this is <hi>faith:</hi> they, <hi>pride</hi> We, <hi>deuotion.</hi> And albeit this aſſurance be in ſome more euident, in ſome more obſcure: (according to the meaſure of the receit of that which giueth teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony) yet are the
<hi>ſonnes</hi> of God <hi>ſealed</hi> with au Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and inuiolable
<hi>Character:</hi> in the beholding whereof they haue an aſſurance of life. Wee <hi>know</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi>)<note place="margin">1. Ioh.
3.2.14.</note> that he <hi>abideth</hi> in vs: wee <hi>know</hi> that we are of the <hi>truth.</hi> We <hi>know</hi> that when hee ſhall appeare, we ſhall be like vnto him. We <hi>know that we are of God.</hi> Heere is then no morall ſuppoſition, no variable <hi>conceipt of Man,</hi> which begets
<hi>anxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty,</hi> and
<hi>perplexity</hi> of <hi>minde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.19.</note> But <hi>(Scientia)</hi> a knowledge which giueth an entrance vnto the
<hi>Thrane</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> with <hi>boldneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>How.</hi>
               </note>Now our laſt Queſtion and greateſt, is how this our <hi>aſſurance</hi> may be obtained? The generality of the meanes (ſaith my <hi>Text</hi>) is <hi>Diligence (Giue rather dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence)</hi> we muſt not ſtand all the day idle in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket.
<hi>An put as dormitanti tibi Confecturos Deos?</hi> Doth any man thinke it ſhall be thruſt into his pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et? There belongs more vnto it, then hold and haue it. The Kingdome of heauen comes not by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.
<hi>(Diligence)</hi> that induſtrious workemaiſter muſt build our aſſurance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or <hi>iuſtum est</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi>) <hi>vt illi conſequantur ſtipendium, qui ſuum commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare reperiuntur obſequium.</hi> The Labourer is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his hire. And as <hi>(Diligence)</hi> our carefull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12976:10"/>is the meanes in generall, ſo in particular muſt we carry this Item with vs, that in our firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out we mount not too high. <hi>Qui neſcit viam ad Mare, Amnem ſibi queras Comitem:</hi> (ſaith the Poet.) The ſureſt way to finde out the Sea, is to be guided by a Riuer. The beginning of our ſearch muſt be in our ſelues: and ſo muſt we goe vp (as by <hi>Iacobs lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>) to the counſell of our God. For in our ſelues hath God ſet ſignes and teſtimonies of our <hi>Calling</hi> &amp; <hi>Election,</hi> which will not deceiue vs. Heere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is our
<hi>Diligence:</hi> our trauaile, our labour to be beſtowed. The tokens or teſtimonies which God hath giuen vs are three: two within vs: One with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vs. Within vs, wee haue firſt a teſtimonie of Gods <hi>Spirit. (Then)</hi> another of our owne. The <hi>Spirit</hi> of God ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> beareth witneſſe, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ther with our
<hi>Spirits,</hi> that we are the ſonnes of God. Without vs: is our new
<hi>obedience.</hi> Make your <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection</hi> ſure:
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by good workes: ſo it is in the vulgar tranſtations. And as this well agreeth with the ſcope of the Text, ſo doth Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> confeſſe, that hee ſawe two <hi>Greeke mannſcripts,</hi> wherein theſe words
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were expreſſed. One witneſſe (ſayth <hi>Baldus</hi>) is no witneſſe <hi>vni testi, ne Catoni quidem credendum est</hi> (ſayth S. <hi>Hierome.</hi> In the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall euery truth ſtand. God therefore hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for vs a threefolde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is a perfect eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. For as the number of three is compleate, which is contained in a beginning: in a middle in an ending. So is this euidence <hi>funiculus triplex,</hi> a perfect teſtimonie. Begunne by Gods Spiritte<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12976:11"/>Seconded with our owne: and ended with good workes. Our firſt euidence in Gods <hi>ſpirit. Et vbi Spiritus teſtatur, ambiguitas non relinquitur</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>) in his fourteenth <hi>Homely</hi> vpon the
<hi>Romans.</hi> And this teſtimonie of the <hi>Spirit</hi> is without exception; neither <hi>Deceiuing:</hi> nor <hi>deceiued:</hi> not
<hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiung:</hi> for it is the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> Not
<hi>deceiued:</hi> for it ſearcheth all things euen the deepe things of God. If an <hi>Angel</hi> ſhould come from heauen vnto vs as he did to
<hi>Marie,</hi> and tell vs in the name of God, that we were <hi>called</hi> &amp; <hi>elected;</hi> would we ſtand in doubt Rather would we not eſteeme him a Meſſenger of moſt ioyfull tidings? But ſo much the more certaine is the teſtimony of Gods <hi>Spirit,</hi> by how much hee is more acquainted with the minde of God then an <hi>Angel</hi> is; and can leſſe deceiue. Yet howſoeuer (as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth)<note place="margin">1. Tim.
4.</note> the <hi>Spirit</hi> ſpeaketh euidentlie ſuch for all that is our naturall <hi>preſumption,</hi> as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dreame they are <hi>Rich,</hi> when in truth they are but poore: boaſt of the Spirit, and are well perſwaded of their <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ection</hi> when they are nothing leſſe. Yea dye in a gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of ſaluation, and yet are damned. A g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e the ſleights of the Diuell, are ſtrong illuſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in many times another teſtimony than euer God gaue vnto vs: eſpecially working vpon the weake heart of man, which being full of ſelfe loue, is eaſily perſwaded of any good to it ſelfe. Two things then for our better ſecurity muſt be obſerued: Firſt how the teſtimony of the ſpirit is framed in vs: Secondly how it may be diſcerned by vs. It is not framed by extraordinary infuſion; or by Enthuſiaſme<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12976:11"/>that is ordinary reuelation without the word. It is no ſuddaine act in the ſoule, or haſty concluſion, without diſcourſe; but made by application of the promiſe of the Goſpell, in the forme of a practique ſilogiſme. The propoſition whereof is this: whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beleeueth in Chriſt, is called: is choſen to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. This is the word of promiſe, which is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and applied to the heart, by the Miniſters of the Goſpell, ſet apart for that purpoſe. Now whileſt a hearer of this word, giues himſelfe to meditate and conſider of the ſame, comes the ſpirit of God, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens his eies, and opens his heart, and giues him a double power: One is, a will to beleeue: and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to beleeue indeed: and that in ſuch a ſort, as a man with freedom of ſpirit, ſhall be able to make the aſſumption, and ſay: But I beleeue in Chriſt: I truſt not to my ſelfe, all my ioy and comfort is in him. And hence ariſeth the bleſſed concluſion, which is the teſtimony of the ſpirit, Therfore am I the child of God, called and elected vnto euerlaſting life. This is the frame of it. Now as the operation of an Angell of God, may be diſcerned from the Spirit of God by the working: for (as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus ſuggerit, ſpiritus ingerit.</hi> So the way to diſcerne the Spirit of God from naturall preſumption, or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanicall illuſion; is by effects. <hi>Ex fructibus cognoſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) ye ſhall know it by the fruits. The fruits to diſcouer it are eſpecially two: Couched together by S.
<hi>Paul</hi> in one peece of a verſe:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> It makes vs crie (<hi>Ahba</hi>) that is Father. The firſt fruit is to crie: to pray earneſtly, out of a touched heart with aſence and feeling of ſinne. We are not able to pray of our<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12976:12"/> ſelues (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>It is the ſpirit that helpeth our infirmities, that maketh intercesſion for vs with ſighes and grones which cannot be vttered.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> 
               <hi>Hence it is called by Zacharie the ſpirit of praier.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zacha. 12.10.</note>
               <hi>And as a foole is knowne by much laughter, ſo is the child of God by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent praier.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 19.28.</note> A wicked man may be partaker of the preaching of the word, may come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may acknowledge the truth of the Goſpell: may profeſſe it with
<hi>Iudas:</hi> may defend it with <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian:</hi> may haue ſome feeling of his ſinnes, ſome ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of conſcience for them: may deſire Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to pray for him; (as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did <hi>Moſes</hi>) as
<hi>Simon Magus</hi> did <hi>Simon Peter</hi>) but pray himſelfe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: vnleſſe we will account the mumbling ouer of mattins for faſhion ſake to be a praying, which a parrot may be taught to doe. Wherefore to crie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, out of an humbled heart for ſinne, with a confidence to be heard, is a principall note of the Spirit of adoption. The ſecond fruit, is a childlike affection to his God (<hi>Abba</hi>) a moſt louing father: which permits not a man vpon euery occaſion to fall into ſinne ſtraightwaies, without miſlike or ſtay: but it moues him to make a conſcience of euerie euill way: to ſtand in feare of the Maieſty of God, whereſoeuer he is. In feare (I ſay) not leaſt he periſh, but leaſt he diſpleaſe: not ingendred by the terror of hell, and is a feare, leſt God ſhould puniſh him: but which commeth from the promiſes of heauen, and is a feare, leaſt his father ſhould forſake him. A filiall feare, <hi>cum dilectione, cum delectatione</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) ioyned with a loue and delight. And he that thus crieth, that is thus affected to God as to his father:<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12976:12"/>This crying, this affection, is neither the conceipt of the fleſh, nor the deceipt of the diuell, but the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Gods ſpirit within him, that giues aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond euidence is the teſtimony of our own hearts, purified and ſanctified in the bloud of Chriſt. And as that of Gods ſpirit muſt goe before, ſo this of our owne, muſt follow after: for what boldneſſe (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>)<note place="margin">1. Cor.
1.4.</note> can we haue with God if our hearts condemne vs? Now the heart teſtifieth by ſpeciall graces imprinted in the ſoule or ſpirit of a man.</p>
            <p>Which haue a double reference,
<list>
                  <item> 1. To our ſinnes.</item>
                  <item> 2. To the mercies of God in Chriſt.</item>
               </list> To our ſinnes, either
<list>
                  <item> 1. Paſt.</item>
                  <item> 2. Preſent,</item>
                  <item> 3. To come.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The grace, which concerneth ſinnes paſt, is a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow for them, occaſioned indeed by ſinne, but ſpringing properly from the apprehenſion of the fauour of our God vnto vs.<note place="margin">2. Cor.
7.10.</note> This begetteth a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in vs, to amend our liues: teacheth vs by confeſſion and ſupplication to cleere our offenees: Compelleth vs to be angry with our ſelues, for our ſinnes committed: to feare, leaſt we fal into the ſame againe: to deſire ſtrength and aſſiſtance againſt them: to be zealous of good duties: and to ſubdue our bodies by reuenging our ſinnes vpon our ſelues. For your godly ſorrow (ſaith <hi>S. Paul</hi>) ſee what care it hath wrought in you? yea what clearing? yea what indignation? yea what feare? yea what vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire? yea what zeale? yea what reuenge?<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12976:13"/>Theſe are the fruits of a ſauing ſorrow. And he who feeleth them for his ſinnes paſt, hath a teſtimony of his owne ſpirit of his calling and election.</p>
            <p>And as a man muſt be a mourner for his ſinnes which are paſt, ſo muſt he play the ſouldier in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſinnes preſent. The next grace then in the heart, which regardeth preſent corruption, is to combat with it.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Plato</hi> was of the mind that in euery man there were two ſoules, but <hi>Paul</hi> tells vs, that in euery man there are two men: ſo ioined together, that the one cannot be without the other, ſo ſeuered aſunder, that the death of the one is the life of the other. Theſe (two) one man is as ancient as the world it ſelfe, the one, deriuing his originall from the earth, the other from heauen. But as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> two dreames were but one famine, ſo theſe two Men, were but one <hi>Adam.</hi> The Lord framed Man of the duſt of the earth, there was one man. And he made Man in his owne image with the breath of life, there is the other Man, and called his name <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> there is both in one. Euer ſince our fall hath there been a combat or deadly warfare betwixt this double <hi>Man.</hi> The inward <hi>Man,</hi> fighting with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. the <hi>Spirit</hi> with the <hi>Fleſh.</hi> The two Twinnes <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> wraſtle together. And though <hi>Eſau</hi> be firſt borne (<hi>prius carnale</hi>) the Carnall the former yet in Gods <hi>Children, Iacob</hi> gets the <hi>bleſsing,</hi> the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall</hi> is the better. Our eſtate is not now like the <hi>Cope</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> aboue the <hi>Moone</hi> free from <hi>ſtorms,</hi> we haue heere the perfection, not of (<hi>Resters</hi>) but of <hi>Runners,</hi> not of our
<hi>Country:</hi> but of the <hi>way,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there are <hi>flawes</hi> and <hi>tempests.</hi> If wee bee a while<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12976:13"/>at a calme: the
<hi>Fleſh</hi> is ready to moleſt vs. And we cannot ſo ſing peace to our ſoules, but the Diuell alſo will caſt his <hi>Crotchets</hi> in: yet if wee take vnto vs the Armour of God, and fight manfully: If we raiſe vp our ſelues vnder the burthen of ſinne, and do ſuch things as are acceptable vnto God (though wee cannot doe them as wee would) if wee finde a ſtriuing in our ſelues, the <hi>Mind fighting with the minde:</hi> the will with the will, the affections with the affections: albeit we cannot vtterlie ouercome: though <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> bee vp in armes; yet if we cauſe the Elder to ſerue the Yonger: though Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites and Iebuſites dwell among the Iſraelires; yet if wee make them our bond ſlaues and hewers of wood: thogh <hi>Sarah</hi> be ſhrewiſh; yet if <hi>Abraham</hi> that is the
<hi>Spirit,</hi> doth beget of <hi>Sara,</hi> (that is the <hi>Fleſh</hi>) a Sonne <hi>Iſaacke</hi> (that is, <hi>Ioy</hi> and <hi>Laughter</hi>) here is good cauſe of Comfort: Another Euidence in our heartes from the reſiſting of Sinnes preſent, that wee ſhall bee ſaued.</p>
            <p>The third grace which reſpecteth ſinne to come: is a care to preuent it. And as the firſt makes vs Mourners: the ſecond Souldiers: ſo this thirde calles vpon vs to bee Watchmen: not to lie a ſleepe till a dead blow bee giuen: but to ſuſpect the firſt ſtrokes of ſinne, not to tarry to bee ſtung, but to feare the leaſt buzzing. This marke of Gods child we find in S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 8.18</note> 
               <hi>He that is borne of God ſinneth not,</hi> but keepeth himſelfe that the wicked one touch him not: that is, hee is circumſpect, hee is carefull to auoide ſinne. And his care is not onely in the ordering of outward actions, but euen of<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12976:14"/>the very thoughts of his heart: <hi>O Lord</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>keepe mee from the way of wickednes:</hi> Where upon Saint
<hi>Ambreſe</hi> obſerueth, that hee would bee kept not from wickednes onely, but from the way too: For, where the Goſpell is of force, it bringeth c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thought into captiuity to the obedience of Chriſt, as Saint
<hi>Paul</hi> doth witneſſe.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.5.</note> And thus much of that part of your inward euidence which reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth ſinne.</p>
            <p>That which concerneth Gods mercies in Chriſt, is twofold.
<list>
                  <item> 1 An earneſt deſire of reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation with God.</item>
                  <item> 2 And ardent loue to Chriſt and his righteouſnes.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt: when as man feeleth himſelfe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed with the burthen of his finnes; when hee apprehendeth the heauy diſpleaſure of God in his conſcience for them: if then conceiuing (his great neede of a Sauiour) hee doth heartily deſire (yea hunger and thirſt to bee at peace with God, in the meritas of Chriſt) no perill being ſo fearefull vnto him, as to bee out of Gods fauour: no bleſſing ſo chearefull; as to bee at vnity with him: vnto ſuch a one, hath Chriſt made moſt comfortable promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which can appertaine to none but the Elect: vnto him ſhall bee giuen of <hi>the Well of the water of life freely:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 21.6.</note> 
               <hi>And this water ſhall bee in him as a Well of water ſpringing vp vnto euerlasting li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 4.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſecond, hee that can ſo highly eſteeme of Chriſt and his righteouſnes, as that hee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip 3.</note> the moſt pretious things that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12976:14"/>are to be but <hi>doung</hi> in <hi>compariſon:</hi> He that can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre Chriſt and his <hi>loue,</hi> before <hi>father</hi> and
<hi>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her, wife</hi> and
<hi>children:</hi> He that hath ſo ſtrong an <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> wrought in his <hi>heart,</hi> as that if his <hi>young childe</hi> ſhould hang about his necke: his mother ſhew her breaſts which gaue him ſucke; his Father lye in the dore to ſtay him from Chriſt: hee could caſt away his childe: contemne his Mother: tread vpon his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: renounce all, <hi>et volare ad vexillum Chriſli</hi> (as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeaketh) &amp; flye to the Banner of his Chriſt (like <hi>Aene as</hi> in the Poet) who when
<hi>Troye</hi> was won, carried away neither kithe nor kinne, <hi>ſed Deos ciuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> but the Gods of the citie: Certainly ſuch a one is marked out to ſaluation: hee hath the ſeale of God vpon him, and (as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith)<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.19</note> he may aſſure his hart before him.</p>
            <p>Euery man will ſay of himſelfe, that hee is thus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ected vnto Chriſt, when as indeede moſt men had rather haue <hi>Eſaus</hi> broth, then <hi>Iacobs</hi> bleſſing. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaſt we be deceiued, wee muſt trye our loue vnto Chriſt by theſe two tokens: Firſt, he that doth rightly eſteem of Chriſt, doth in like manner eſteem of thoſe which are his members. <hi>Tuſtis et Amor Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari non poſſunt,</hi> as the Cough cannot be couered, no more can loue, it will breake out to others: <hi>Hee that receiueth a Prophet in the name of a Prophet ſhal receiue a Prophets reward. He that receiueth a righteous man in the name of a righteous man, ſhall receiue the reward of the righteous.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10</note> It is hee that loueth Chriſt, <hi>and ſhall dwell in his Tabernacle, who maketh much of him that feareth God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 15.</note> And heereby doe wee know that wee are raiſed from death to life, becauſe wee loue the<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12976:15"/>Brethren (that is) ſuch as are the members of Chriſt, euen becauſe they are ſo.<note place="margin">1. Ioh.
3.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is a token of our loue to Chriſt, if we loue his comming, that we may haue full participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and fellowſhip with him. The carnall man ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth little: he hath no ſenſe nor ſight of his comming but as the Oxe is fatted in the paſture, and the Birde ſingeth ſweetlie, and feedeth without feare: yet ſodainly one is carried to the ſlaughter, the other is taken in the ſnare, ſo are worldlings drowned in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity: and ſeldome thinke of: much leſſe wiſh for: the comming of Chriſt. Others, who are ſtrong in ſinne, and which force the wrath of God againſt them) doe tremble and quake at the remembrance of his comming. They wiſh it might eyther neuer bee, or euer be deferred. Oh; it is moſt terrible vnto them, once to thinke that a day will come, when all of them ſhall be cited before Gods Iudgement ſeat: when as all their workes, their words, their thoughts ſhall be reuealed: when as a heauy doome of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhall be pronounced againſt them: when to lye hidden wil be impoſſible for them, and to appear will bee intollerable to them. The conſideration of theſe terrors of the Lord, dooth affright them ſo, as if the Diuell were at their dores.) But the children of God (who loue Chriſt) crye Lord Ieſu come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Now, they are as wardes; then ſhall they come to their owne. Now are they in the skirmiſh; then ſhall they bee in the victorie. Now are they in the tempeſtuous Sea, then ſhall they bee in the quiet Hauen. Now in the heat of the day, then in the reſt of the Euening. Now are they abſent from Chriſt,<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12976:15"/>Then ſhall they follow him whereſoeuer he goeth. And why ſhould they not be ioyfull at his comming to iudge them, who came to be iudged for them? A louing Spouſe deſires to bee in the boſome of her husband: and ſuch is the longing of the Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt: for, if being abſent from him, he doth ſo enrich vs with grace, and tokens of his loue: Lorde, how will he hugge vs, and embrace vs, when we are preſent with him? <hi>Si ſie es bonus ſequentibus te, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis futurus es conſequentibus</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>)? The very deſire then we haue, wholy to enioy the fellowſhippe of our Chriſt, makes vs to lift vp our heades, and to loue his comming: which is another Argument vnto vs that wee ſhall be ſaued, becauſe <hi>a Crowne of Righteouſneſſe is laide vp for them that loue his appearing</hi> (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth tell vs.)<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There remaineth now the laſt and outward eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our calling and Election, that is <hi>new obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> our endeauour by good works to obey Gods commandements: for hereby are we <hi>ſure we know him, if wee keepe his commandements:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.3.</note> we neede not to wring or wreſt a good deed out of a good man, as one would wring veriuice out of a Crab. He is a <hi>tree,</hi> that hath euer ſome figges vpon him. But leaſt here againe, wee ſhould chance to deceiue our ſelues:
<hi>The obedience</hi> (which is the infallible marke of Gods childe) muſt not bee a <hi>halfe but a whole o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the whole man: To the whole law of God.</hi> In the whole courſe of our liues.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt it muſt bee obedience of the whole man;
<hi>in Body, in Soule, in Spirit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ.
3.13.</note> Wee muſt <hi>ſummon</hi> all our parts and powers together like a <hi>Cryer,</hi> to pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>forme
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12976:16"/> a ſeruice vnto our God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it muſt bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience <hi>To</hi> the whole law: for the condition of the Law is meerely Copulatiue; All the parts of it are linked one to another. He thats bound to <hi>One,</hi> is bound to <hi>All?</hi> Hee that makes no
<hi>Conſcience</hi> to keepe <hi>One,</hi> when <hi>Occaſion</hi> is offered will breake <hi>any. Herod</hi> gaue <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> the hearing in many things, but would not leaue his <hi>Brothers Wife: Iudas</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>preathed the Goſpell,</hi> but would in no caſe forſake his <hi>Couetouſnes: Saul</hi> was content to ſlay ſome of the Amalekites, but left <hi>Agag</hi> aliue. But this peece meale obedience is nothing worth: He that faileth in <hi>One,</hi> is guilty of
<hi>All.</hi> For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the rigour of the law is abated vnto vs in Chriſt, (who accepteth of him, that doth what hee can doe, as if he were one that did what he ſhould doe) yet may not the Iſraelites hault between two opinions. <hi>Mongrells</hi> in Religion were deuoured by Lyons. But I ſhall nor <hi>be confounded</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>)<note place="margin">Pſal.
119.6</note> 
               <hi>when I haue reſpect to (All) thy commandements:</hi> Vpright Obedience then doth enlarge it ſelfe to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery precept.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, it muſt bee Obedience in the whole courſe of our liues. One Swallow makes not a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; wee may not iudge of a man by an action or two, but by the whole tenor of his life. Such as the courſe of a manslife is, ſuch is the Man, though through corruption of nature, he faile in this or that particular: yet doth not Gods child dwell in ſinne, but renues his repentance for his ſeuerall ſlippes. Indeed
<hi>Terrigina fratres,</hi> the earth-borne broode, they are like to the Graſhoppers, which<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12976:16"/>ſometimes leape a little vpwards, but preſently fall to the ground againe: So theſe haue ſome light and ſhort motions to goodneſſe, but they quicklie returne to their olde affections againe. They loue <hi>vanity</hi> more then <hi>truth, droſſe</hi> more then <hi>golde,</hi> the <hi>earth</hi> more then <hi>heauen,</hi> the
<hi>world</hi> more then him that <hi>made and redeemed the world. Fowles</hi> that feed groſſely neuer flie high, and they that fill their hearts with things below, cannot bee but earthly minded: but the true ſonnes of God (through in Infirmity without perfection, yet in ſincerity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſſimulation) haue their conuerſation as Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of new Ieruſalem which is aboue. The workes of darkeneſſe are weariſome vnto them, becauſe they are the children of Light. The fruites of the fleſh are loathſome vnto them, becauſe they are renued by the Spirrt of God. They are
<hi>In</hi> the world, but not <hi>Of</hi> the world. They vſe the world as though they vſed it not. They eſteeme their houſes as Innes to reſt in, not as manſions to dwell in for euer. All their worldly honours, pleaſures, profites, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they vſe as ſtaues in their hands, the better to bring them to their iourneyes end. Thus doe the Sonnes of God, <hi>walke in a whole obedience of the whole man: in their whole life,</hi> which giueth an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence vnto them of their Calling and election.</p>
            <p>Now (my beloued) <hi>Hic ſpecimen ſpecitur, hic certamen cernitur:</hi> here is now the main point the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſumme, the whole duety of a Chriſtiau. Wilt thou bee ſure thou ſhalt bee ſaued? beware of an idle ſpeculation of faith. Giue all diligence to<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12976:17"/>haue the teſtimony of Gods Spirit rightly formed in thee. Giue all diligence to haue it truely diſcerned by thee. <hi>Pray vnto thy God earnestly, obey him lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly, mourne for ſinnes past heartily, ſtriue with ſinnes preſent ſtoutely, prenent ſinnes to come carefully.</hi> Giue all diligence to ſeek after reconcilement with thy God, with a thirſt vnto it, value Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe at the higheſt price, expreſſe thy mind herein, by loue to his Members, by deſire of his comming, holde not heauen with thy two ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, but with thy whole hand, and ſtudy to yeeld obedience to all the lawes of God, at all times, in body, in ſoule, in ſpirit, beginne quickly, increaſe dayly, continue in thy obedience conſtantly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hipocriſie: Giue (rather) diligence, (that is) before all things, in the prime of thy youth, in the beginning of thy dayes: (Giue rather) diligence (that is) Aboue all things, aboue a Dukedome, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Princedom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, a Kingdome, to make thy calling and election ſure.</p>
            <p>I haue read a ſtory of an Abbot, who beholding what coſt a woman had beſtowed in attiring of her ſelfe, fell a weeping. Oh (ſaid hee) what a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is this, that a woman ſhould beſtow more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vpon the dreſſing of her body, then wee haue done in the adorning of our ſoules. That ſhe ſhould put more ornaments vpon her head, then wee haue beene carefull to put into our hearts. And truely (beloued) this is a common calamity wee wiſh for heauen, but contend for the earth. <hi>Maries</hi> part is better: but <hi>Marthaes</hi> the greater. Let vs therefore giue the (rather) diligence, to make our Calling<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12976:17"/>and Election ſure. What if the world ſets on good wine at the firſt? it will afterwards bring that which is worſe. What if it entertaine with mirth? it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes with mourning: It is like a Candle ſhining brightly, but ending in a ſtinking ſmoake. What doth the Fleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> afforde? but ſinne? What the Diuel? but torments, what the worlde? but trouble. Make therefore thy calling and election ſure, and then haſt thou righteouſneſſe and ioy, and peace in the holie Ghoſt: Righteouſneſſe againſt ſinne, Ioy againſt Torture, Peace againſt trouble. <hi>Oh ſeeke not death in the error of your ſoules</hi> (ſaith Wiſdome) and <hi>deſtroy not your ſelues in the works of your owne hands.</hi> Make haſte to make ſaluation ſure. A foole will deſire to doe that in the end, when hee commeth to had I wiſt, which hee that is wiſe will doe in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Doe people commend thee for a good and a iuſt man? I, but what if thine owne heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth thee? Are all men friendly to thee? I but what if God bee thine enemy? Surely, if thine aſſiſtance were an hoaſt of armed Souldiers, if thy friends were the Princes and Monarkes of the earth; if thy poſſeſſions were as large as from Eaſt to weſt, if thy me ate were as Manna from heauen, and thy apparrell as coſtly as the Ephod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> if euery day were as glorious vnto thee, as the day was to Chriſt when he aroſe from his graue;<note place="margin">1. Ioh.
8.18</note> yet who dares meete with the anger of the Lord of hoaſts? who can put to ſilence the voice of Deſperation? who can make a Couenant with hell, to ſpare thee? or an agreement with the Diuell to lay no claim vnto thee? Wherefore giue all diligence to make thy <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12976:18"/>calling and Election ſure. It is a greater toyle (I confeſſe) but profite will make men labour hard; Will carry our deſires very farre. The dangers of the Sea are made delightſome by the expectation of gaine. The tediouſneſſe of Phiſicke is mitigated by the hope of health: <hi>Nullus labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r dur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri debet</hi> (ſaieth <hi>Hierome</hi>) <hi>quo gloria aternitatis acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur.</hi> Let vs not giue ouer, wee ſhall bee rewarded according to our labours. It is a diligence (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) that is ſubiect to much diſgrace, to many a ſcoffe and floute amongſt wicked men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <hi>Sed durate &amp; voſmet rebus ſeruate ſecundis:</hi> but bee not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed the labour is for life: Saluation lyeth at the ſtake. Hath
<hi>Mutius</hi> patiently endured burning? <hi>Socrates</hi> poyſon?
<hi>Cato</hi> death? Haue heathen men been conſtant for ſo ſmall are compence, as a popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar applauſe, and prayſe in the world? How much (rather) ought Chriſtians for the Kingdom of God? Wherfore (my Brethren) if heauen be our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, if Chriſt bee our treaſure, if Glory bee our hope, let vs giue all diligence to make our Calling and Election ſure, which grace God grant vnto vs for his mercies ſake, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:12976:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SINNERS CONVERSION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>And behold a woman in the Citie which was a ſinner, when ſhee knew that Ieſus ſate at Table in the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees houſe, ſhe brought a boxe of ointment:</p>
                  <p>And ſhe ſtood at his feete behind him weeping, and began to waſh his feete with teares, and did wipe them with the haires of her head, and kiſſed his feete, and annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them with the ointment.</p>
                  <bibl>Luke
7. verſ. 37.38.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words, containe in them the <hi>Conuerſation</hi> and
<hi>Conuerſion</hi> of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which preſſed vpon Chriſt, as hee ſat at meat in a Phariſies houſe: Her <hi>Conuerſation,</hi> is deſcribed in the beginning of the 37. verſe. <hi>And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a woman in the city which was a Sinner.</hi> Her <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion,</hi> appeareth in the words following. When ſhe had knowledge of Chriſt, ſhe brought a <hi>Box of ointment;</hi> ſhee ſtood at his feete behinde him, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: ſhee beganne to water his feete with teares: ſhee wiped them with the haires of her head: ſhee<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12976:19"/>kiſſed them: ſhee anoynted them with her oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note>Firſt of her
<hi>Conuerſation:</hi> The firſt word of the Text ſetteth me at a ſtand, and bids me <hi>Behold.</hi> Surely there is ſome ſtrange matter following wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy obſeruation. For ſo much doth (<hi>Ecce Behold</hi>) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in the Scriptures. In the ſeuenth of <hi>Eſay, Ecce virgo: Behold a virgine:</hi> Why? what is the matter? She ſhall conceiue, and bring forth a Childe. A <hi>virgine conceiue?</hi> A <hi>virgine</hi> bring foorth? This is ſtrange indeede. So heere (<hi>Ecce mulier</hi>) behold a woman. A woman, which at the firſt was the cauſe of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ns deſtruction: is now become the exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſe of mans <hi>Conuerſion.</hi> A woman weake by
<hi>nature,</hi> is become ſtrong by <hi>grace:</hi> A woman in
<hi>ſexe,</hi> is become a man in <hi>action.</hi> A woman, who when ſhe was at the beſt, was ſoone ſeduced: is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Ioy of Angels, the aſtoniſhment to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels: a ſhame vnto thoſe, who are ſlow to
<hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> &amp; vnto ſuch as are willing to come to Chriſt, a
<hi>Patterne</hi> and <hi>Inſtruction. Ecce mulier, Beholde a woman:</hi> Though this be rare, yet this is not all. For <hi>Behold, a woman, a Sinner.</hi> It is a harder thing, <hi>to ſterne a ſhip in a tempeſt:</hi> then to ſtand vpon the <hi>ſhore.</hi> A harder thing, to rid a man from danger: then to keepe him in ſafety: and wiſedome is more iuſtified of a childe which ariſeth; then of that which doth not fall.
<hi>Behold</hi> then <hi>a woman, a ſinner. Sinners,</hi> are
<hi>blinde,</hi> are <hi>fooles,</hi> are <hi>ſlaues.</hi> Firſt they are
<hi>blinde:</hi> For howſoeuer the children of this world, would ſeeme to ſee more then the children of light; as owles are ſharper ſighted in the night time, but dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in the day, yet can they not poſſibly perceiue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12976:19"/>thoſe things which are of God. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2.14. Though there be light in <hi>Goſhen</hi> amongſt Gods people, yet will there bee blacke and palpable darkneſſe in the land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> amongſt the wicked. <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.22. That which is manifeſt to Saints, vnto whom God doth make knowen the riches of his wiſedome: is hidden vnto worldly men. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.26. Theſe may haue the name to ſee, as the Church of <hi>Sardi</hi> had the name to liue: but as that <hi>Church</hi> was ſtarke dead <hi>Apocal.</hi> 3. ſo theſe are ſoone blinde; their mindes are blinded. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2.3.14. Yea their very hearts are full of darkeneſſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 21. <hi>verſe.</hi> Secondly,
<hi>Sinners</hi> are <hi>fooles,</hi> neither let it ſeeme ſtrange vnto vs, that ſubtile ſinners ſhould be ſimple fooles. For he that is called wiſe <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.11. in the 12. of <hi>Luke</hi> 20. <hi>verſe,</hi> is termed a foole. <hi>A good Gramarian</hi> (ſayth <hi>Origen</hi>) vpon the
16. to the Romans, <hi>may be a foole at a handy craft, a good Gouernour a bad Phyſitian, and men of deepe reach in wordly matters, plaine ideots in heauenly wiſedome.</hi> There was a time I confeſſe when wee had a threefold knowledge which was moſt excellent: of all things created: of our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour: of our ſelues: <hi>Sed Adam dam raperet Diuinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, perdidit foelicitatem.</hi> (ſayth S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) But ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fall, we are become like bruit beaſts voyde of vnderſtanding. We haue a threefold ignorance in ſtead of our knowledge: of all things created: of our Creatour: and of our ſelues. Hence it is, that ſinnes are ſayd by Saint
<hi>Augustine</hi> to bee the ſoules darkneſſe: That <hi>Gregory</hi> calles offendours fooles: and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the <hi>wiſedome of the world enmity vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Sinners</hi> are <hi>ſlaues:</hi> Man was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12976:20"/>the Lord of all creatures, but by ſinne he is made a slaue to euery vilde thing. A miſer is a ſlaue to his mony: a glutton, to his throat: a chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke man to anger: a laſciuious man, to pleaſure. Seruants are not more at the beck of their maiſters, then ſinners are at the command of vices. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that in the 8. of
<hi>Iohn</hi> 34. <hi>verſe: Whoſoeuer committeth ſinne, is the ſeruant of the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and which makes the ſlauery the worſe, they are thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vaſſals vnto Sathan, who neuer ſuffreth them to reſt, but alwayes ſetteth them about his drudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, till he hath wearied them in the way of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>and brought them to deſtruction. Wiſdom the</hi> 5. 7. <hi>verſe.</hi> Wherefore in that a blinde woman, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth after the light: a fooliſh woman, after wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: a woman in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>auery, after her redeemer. This in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reaſeth the wonder: <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce mulier pecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trix: Behold a woman a ſinner.</hi> And yet his not this all nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Behold a woman: A ſinner:</hi> in a city: a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, a knowen ſinner; blazed ouer a whole city, notorious and infamous. Though there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (no doubt) in the city: yet was none like vnto her. Shee had loſt her honour: her good name: and through cuſtome in ſinne, was become careleſſe of reports. A young offendour, is not impudent on the ſuddaine, but hath ſome remorſe when hee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. He that putteth on new cloathes, will at the firſt be carefull where hee ſitteth, leaſt hee ſtaine or defile them, but being once ſoyled ouer, he little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth where he clappes himſelfe downe: ſo a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in ſinne, will haue ſome care of his conſcience, but an inueterate tranſgreſſour is without reſpect.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12976:20"/>a horſe at the firſt is quicke vpon the ſpurre, but a continuall digging in his ſides makes him dull, <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders</hi> haue ſenſe of ſinne in the beginning, but cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome taketh the feeling of ſinne away. A Candle lately put out with a little puffe, is lighted againe: but if it bee loug extinguiſhed, it is not ſo ſoone reuiued. A young Sinner is eaſily conuerted, but olde Soakers are hardly reclaimed. Behold then a matter full of wonder, A woman a Sinner, an vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, an infamous Sinner, <hi>tota ciuitate</hi> in a whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, doth now beginne to make a conſcience of her actions, hauing had her light long put out, now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to bee enlightned by Grace, hauing liued long in iniquity, yet now beginneth to haue a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of her former life, to leaue her ſinne, to ſeeke after her Sauiour. This truely is exceeding ſtrange, ſeldome ſeene in the world. And therefore no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell though there bee an (<hi>Ecce</hi>) a word of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion prefixed: <hi>Behold a woman in a City which was a ſinner.</hi> My Text giueth mee leaue, and her carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age compelleth mee, to make after her a further ſearch. Firſt, who this woman was? Secondly, why her name is concealed? Thirdly, what was her Sinne? Fourthly, where was this City?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">question </seg>
               </label> For the firſt: <hi>Origen</hi> with
<hi>Theophilact</hi> tels vs that there were three, <hi>Mary Magdalens,</hi> wherof (as they ſay) this was one. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> (with whom agreeth Saint <hi>Barnard</hi>) is of opinion that there were but two, whereof one was the ſiſter of <hi>Lazarns,,</hi> and the other, this woman. <hi>S. Auguſtine, S. Gregory,</hi> and <hi>Beda</hi> ſay plainely, there was but one <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> making this, and the ſiſter of <hi>Lazarus</hi> and of <hi>Martha</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:12976:21"/>to be the ſame, vnto whom there were many ſinnes remitted: and out of whom there were many diuels remooued. And albeit ſome thing might be obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the contrary, yet for that I finde it to be the common opinion of ancient times, I am willing to embrace it, the rather for that ſhe was one of them, which followed Chriſt out of
<hi>Galile</hi> where this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident fell out: As we finde in the beginning of the next chapter which makes it more probable. This woman then was <hi>Mary Magdalen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">question </seg>2</label> Secondly, why would not the Euangeliſt call her by her name? was it becauſe ſhee was ſo knowen a ſinner in all the city? as that ſhee had thereby (as it were) loſt her proper name? Indeed as by good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, names of honour are many times pocured (as <hi>Aristotle</hi> for his knowledge is called the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, Tullie</hi> for his eloquence the <hi>Oratour</hi>) ſo for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill deedes are there oftentimes faſtened vpon vs Nicke-names of diſgrace. As <hi>a contentious fellow</hi> may in time be called, <hi>a towne-wrangler, a couetous man, a citie miſer, a flattering Preacher, a court claw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe:</hi> Such perhaps was <hi>Maries</hi> cafe. Shee was ſo wretched and ſhameleſſe a ſinner, as in ſtead of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> ſhe was called the
<hi>city-ſinner.</hi> Or was her name ſuppreſſed to teach others a leſſon, that when wee are about to publiſh the defects of men, we ſhould conceale their names? ſo doth Saint <hi>Luke</hi> in his 16. chapter: where deſcribing a rich Glutton he tels of his cruelty, he ſpareth not his particular ſinnes, yet doth he not publiſh or proclaime his name: Our ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred muſt be againſt the ſinnes of men, and not the men themſelues. Or is ſhe nameleſſe, to teach all <pb n="37" facs="tcp:12976:21"/>ſinners, that howſoeuer they heere ſtriue, to make their names great: to call their lands after their names <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. yet that God will not acknowledge them? that before him they ſhall be nameleſſe? not once remembring them? to giue his allowance of them? Theſe are likely to be the cauſes why <hi>Mary</hi> is heere vnnamed, and in place of <hi>Marie</hi> called a ſinner.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">question </seg>
               </label> But what fowle ſinne had ſhe committed? Some are of opinion that ſhe was vnchaſte, yet not in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: but only in minde and affection, and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being vſed to decke her ſelfe wantonly in light attire, ſhe gat the name of a ſinner. It is commonly found true, that outward attire is the token of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſpoſition, yet for that publike cenſure paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vpon none where ſinne is ſecret, and that the Euangeliſt nameth her a <hi>ſinner in a city, a knowen of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendour,</hi> it cannot chooſe, but that her offences were publike in her outward actions. Others ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhee was a common whore, proſtituting her body to euery commer, but this (mee thinketh) is too ſharpe a cenſure. For ſuch (for the moſt part) are poore and miſerable, and know not readily other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to relieue themſelues: but
<hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> was well deſcended of good wealth: ſhe miniſtred vnto Chriſt and his diſciples out of her owne abundance. And therefore it is not likely that ſhe would betake herſelfe to ſo baſe a trade: Moſt probable it is, that amongſt other of her ſinnes, whoredome was one, that ſhe had giuen herſelfe to idleneſſe, and ſo fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into filthy luſt, which is a ſinne ſubiect to great reproach, eſpecially in a woman of eminent rancke <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12976:22"/>none more, for which cauſe ſhe was publiquely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and termed a ſinner in all the city.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">question </seg>4</label> This city out of Queſtion was the city <hi>Naim</hi> in <hi>Galile,</hi> of which wee reade in the eleuenth verſe of this chapter: which our Euangeliſt in this place na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not: being needleſſe without cauſe to repeat one thing twice. Heere did Chriſt raiſe to life the widowes dead ſon. Heere did he raiſe to grace this ſinfull woman. In this prouince of <hi>Galile</hi> was <hi>Mary</hi> borne, in a towne called <hi>Magdaleel,</hi> of which we read in the nineteenth of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> and of which towne ſhee tooke her name (<hi>Magdalen</hi>), Now in this city of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile</hi> ſhe hearing of the fame of Chriſt, and being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in her minde, with the ſtrangeneſſe of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, wrought vpon the widowes ſonne: being alſo touched with the ſpirit of God, and reſoluing with her ſelfe, that this was the
<hi>Meſsias</hi> that was to come; we may well conceiue (by reaſon of the Sequel her <hi>ſpeedy Conuerſion</hi> which followed) that ſhe thus rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned within her ſoule. Surely, he that hath reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to life a dead young man: can likewiſe giue life vnto mee, who am deade in my ſinnes: Hee that onely by a (Touch) cauſed the men that bare the corps to ſtay: can compell theſe to ceaſe which are carrying me to Hell. My beauty, my riches, my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, my youthfull yeeres, they are now tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting mee into the hands of death. I will goe vnto this Chriſt: it may bee, hee will vouchſafe to touch me with his hand of mercy, and can ſe theſe porters to ſtay. When a widdow cryed for the death of her ſonne, hee was mooued with compaſſion towards her. If I then who am motherleſſe goe and bewaile
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12976:22"/>mine <hi>owne eſtate:</hi> if I water his feet with mine
<hi>owne teares</hi> there is hope of mercy for me. He that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all ſinners to repentance, will not deſpiſe mee, though I bee a ſinner. Surely this is that Prophet which is ſent to viſit vs: I will runne vnto this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: I will returne vnto my God from whom I haue gone aſtray. And forthwith (ſayth the Text) <hi>when ſhe knew that Ieſus ſat at the Table, in the Phariſies houſe,</hi> ſhee went vnto him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conuerſion.</hi>
               </note>And heere doth our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt begin to deſcribe her <hi>Conuerſion.</hi> Wherein hee imitateth a skilfull painter, who firſt draweth out the lineaments of his picture, with a coale or blacke lead and then layeth on liuely colours. So doth S. <hi>Luke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> firſt he noteth out <hi>Marie</hi> with a black coale, and now hee ſetteth her out with beautifull and perfect colours.</p>
            <p>This firſt thing obſeruable in her <hi>Conuerſion</hi> is her knowledge &amp; with all her ſpeed: <hi>when ſhe knew: then ſhe went Knowledge</hi> is the firſt ſtep to <hi>amendment of life: knowledge of Chriſt: knowledge of our ſelues</hi> (<hi>both in this woman</hi>) For vnto a ſound <hi>Conuerſion</hi> theſe three things muſt concurre. 1. <hi>A heauenly light in our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> 2. <hi>A holy heat in our will and affections.</hi> 3. <hi>The ſtrength of Gods arme in our works and actions.</hi> Now a heauenly light in the vnderſtanding muſt go before. The firſt thing, which God made in the framing of the world was light, and the firſt thing alſo which he worketh in our <hi>conuerſion</hi> is light, a true <hi>knowledge</hi> in our <hi>vnderſtanding.</hi> This <hi>light,</hi> this <hi>heat</hi> this ſtrength of action had this bleſſed
<hi>conuert.</hi> Firſt ſhe knew, there was her <hi>light;</hi> Then ſhee carried a <hi>Box of oyntment,</hi> there was her <hi>heat:</hi> Then ſhe ſtood:<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12976:23"/>ſhe wept, ſhe watered, ſhe wiped, ſhe
<hi>kiſſed,</hi> ſhe <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted Chriſts feet;</hi> Heere was her ſtrength in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now as the firſt <hi>degree</hi> vnto amendment of
<hi>life</hi> is <hi>knowledge: knowledge</hi> of God whom we haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended: and <hi>knowledge</hi> of our ſelues who are <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours</hi>) according to that in the 51 <hi>Pſalme, Waſh me O God from mine iniquities and clenſe me from my ſins,</hi> (ſayth <hi>Dauid</hi>) why ſo? Becauſe I know mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and my ſinnes are alwaies before me) So the ſecond ſtep to <hi>Conuerſion,</hi> is preſently to goe vnto him, that can heale, that can pardon, that can cure our infirmities. Thus went this woman on, ſhe had knowledge of Chriſt, and then forthwith ſhe goeth vnto him. She knew that her ſins were like ſnakes in her boſome, which ſhe would not (hauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them) ſleepe with all, but by and by labour to rid herſelfe from them. Vnhappy <hi>Pharaoh</hi> being plagued with frogges in his <hi>Bed, in his ouen,</hi> in his kneading <hi>troughes</hi> and all his
<hi>chambers,</hi> feare cauſed him to ſeeke vnto God: but when
<hi>Moſes</hi> ſayd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him <hi>Exodus</hi> 8. 9. <hi>verſe,</hi> When ſhall I pray for thee that theſe frogges may be deſtroyed, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth in the tenth verſe, that he ſhould doe it to Morrow. It had beene fitter for a man in his caſe to haue requeſted <hi>Moſes</hi> to pray preſently, but hee was content to deferre and put off his deliuerance. Many are there in the worlde at this day, iuſt of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſtampe: who hauing their ſinnes croking in their conſciences (as the frogges craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in <hi>Pharaohes</hi> chambers) are yet contented to delay their
<hi>Conuerſion</hi> from day to day, To Morrow (ſay they) or ſome time heereafter will ſerue the<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12976:23"/>turne. But <hi>Marie</hi> was of another minde, for being a woman (whoſe vſuall commendation is to keepe at home) the leaueth her owne houſe: beeing a ſinner: ſhe ſteppeth into the houſe of a <hi>Phariſie</hi> (who could not abide the preſence of a Sinner) ſhe made no bones (contrary to the rule of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty) to thruſt herſelfe amongeſt a company that ſat at meat: nothing could withhold her from the houſe where her Sauiour was, <hi>vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> egeno inutilis pud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> (ſayth the Prouerbe) ouermuch ſhamefaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is no profitable vertue for a beggar. <hi>Marie</hi> therefore takes not counſell with the world: ſhee reſpects not the ſpeech of men: (which many times cauſe vs to ſurceaſe from good actions) ſhe feared not the mockes and ſcoffes of the <hi>Phariſies,</hi> ſhe ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not till Chriſt had dined and come foorth with his diſciples: ſhe forgat circumſtances of behauiour: And remembred nothing but God and her ſinnes: when ſhee knew where Chriſt was, ſhee could not reſt till ſhee came vnto him. Why? could ſhe not haue inuited Chriſt vnto her owne houſe as <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Zache</hi> did (who were alſo ſinners?) She knew that hee receiued ſinners: did eat with ſinners: I but <hi>Mary</hi> made more haſte then ſo: ſhee had fire in her bowels, the Spirit of God was as a flame within her. Beſide ſhe was an humbled and a broken hearted ſinner deeming herſelfe now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorthy to receiue Chriſt vnder the roofe of her houſe: if like a dog ſhe might wait at his feet, and there receiue but the crums of his goodnes &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſhe thought that enough for her. A notable example for vs to follow; teaching vs in our<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12976:24"/>neceſſities, both
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whom, and how to goe, euen to ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e vnto our God with a broken heart. So did the Centurion in the third verſe of this Chapter. So did the Cananitiſh woman, <hi>Math.</hi> 15: So <hi>Dauid</hi> in all his troubles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Lord</hi> (ſayeth he) Pſalme 143. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer mee from all mine enemies, for I hide mee vnder the ſhadow of thy wings, that I may bee defended by thy power.</hi> So did <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> who to auoide the Rage of the people, betooke themſelues vnto the Tabernacle of their God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. Vnto this courſe are wee inuited by our Sauiour himſelfe in the 11. of <hi>Mathew, Come vnto mee you that trauell and are heauy laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi> Who euer cried vnto God and was not heard? who euer ſought him with his heart, and did not finde him? who euer ſhrowded himſelfe vnder the ſhadow of his wings and was not protected by him? As a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is pittifull vnto his owne children, ſo hath the Lord mercy of them that feare him, hee knoweth whereof wee are made, hee remembreth that we are but duſt. When Kings are in their Courts, and keepe their Priuy Chambers, none may ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, nor yet approch neere them, but Nobles and parſonages of great account: but if they walke into the fieldes, take a iourney, or ride a hunting, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſhepheard and Peaſant of the Country may haue free acceſſe and ſpeake his minde. So may wee ſay of Chriſt, being in his glory, in the Court of heauen, in the Chamber of his Maieſty, thoſe who familiarly &amp; neerely conuerſed with him, were Angels, Archangels, Principalities and Powers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but being made man, and become a Traueller in<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12976:24"/>this worlde, Publicans, Theeues, Harlots, noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sinners, they came vnto him. He ſpeaketh, he giueth audience to them: for <hi>Mary</hi> a great Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner reſorted vnto him, and was receiued.</p>
            <p>The Pelagian heretikes, for that <hi>Mary</hi> went vnto Chriſt, conclude from hence, that man hath free wil and power in his owne nature to ſeeke after God. But the truth is, that he who <hi>receiued Mary,</hi> did alſo make her <hi>come.</hi> Therefore doth <hi>Gregory</hi> call Chriſt, both <hi>trahentem</hi> and <hi>ſuſcipientem,</hi> the <hi>drawer</hi> and the <hi>receiuer.</hi> Riuers runne howerly into the Sea, yet doth not the Sea thereby ouerſlow the banckes, becauſe (as the Preacher tells vs) out of the Sea did they firſt proceed. Secretly, doth the Sea by pores and hidden veines ſend his waters out, &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely by riuers receiueth them home againe. Euen ſo did Chriſt with this woman, he called her <hi>ſecretly,</hi> he inſtilled <hi>deuotion, loue, repentance,</hi> into her heart: he called her vnto him by priuate <hi>inſpiration,</hi> but he receiued her openly, as the Sea doth the riuers. The gifts of grace, which after an inuiſible manner did iſſue from him, by a viſible returning, were made acceptable vnto him. Surely, if Chriſt had not <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Mary</hi> had neuer thought of comming. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit came (ſaith <hi>Ezechiel</hi> in his ſecond chapter) and ſet me vpon my feet: If the ſpirit had not entred, the prophet had not been raiſed: neither can ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners riſe, till Gods ſpirit raiſe them vp: they cannot goe, till they be mooued. They are not vnlike the
<hi>Eccho</hi> in the wood; for as the <hi>Eccho</hi> hath no power to ſpeake firſt, but onely to <hi>anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo is it with all kinde of ſinners, Gods voice muſt ſound, before<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12976:25"/>they haue power to ſpeake: He muſt <hi>draw,</hi> before they can <hi>obey:</hi> Hee muſt often <hi>call,</hi> yet will they ſlowly <hi>anſwer.</hi> And herein alſo doe they reſemble the <hi>Eccho,</hi> which though many words be ſpoken, yeelds but few againe. <hi>Mary</hi> then being <hi>priuately called,</hi> did <hi>openly come.</hi> Teaching vs hereby to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our
<hi>inward calling,</hi> by our <hi>outward comming.</hi> For <hi>Mary</hi> being <hi>called,</hi> ſhe <hi>anſwered,</hi> ſhe <hi>came,</hi> ſhe
<hi>came preſently,</hi> and ſhe <hi>came</hi> not <hi>empty.</hi> For as it followeth in the Text, ſhe brought <hi>a box of oyntment</hi> with her. That whereof ſhe made ſo high account, wherwith ſhe annointed and perfumed her ſelfe, when ſhe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued like a wanton: that ſweet and precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhe brought vnto Chriſt. Was it for that her ſinnes were vnſauorie, and therefore would come with <hi>odours?</hi> Indeed in the
30. of Exodus we read, that before the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> for
<hi>ſinne</hi> was offered, <hi>Incenſe</hi> (by the law) was to be burned. So perhaps did this <hi>Sinner,</hi> ſhe came firſt with her <hi>ſweet ſmelling oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> leſt by the ſtench of her <hi>ſinnes</hi> ſhee ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her Sauiour. Or was it rather to prepare him with her gift, and therefore did beare him this <hi>box of oyntment?</hi> This was
<hi>Iacobs</hi> policie toward his brother <hi>Eſau.</hi> Hee gaue gifts vnto him to preuent his <hi>anger,</hi> Gen. 32. or was it for that God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that none ſhould appeare before him? <hi>Exo.</hi> 32. Being therefore now about to preſent her ſelfe vnto her God, to ſhow her <hi>ſorrow</hi> for her <hi>ſinnes,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe her <hi>obedience</hi> vnto his law. Did ſhee iudge it meet for her (according to the law) to come with ſomething in her hand? or it may be bicauſe ſhee thought him to be the
<hi>Meſsias</hi> to come, and for that<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12976:25"/>ſhee ſaw him indued with more than humane power. She iudged him worthy of honour, and therefore brought him a <hi>box</hi> of <hi>pretious</hi> oyntment: that after the manner of that nation, by annointing of him ſhee might giue honour vnto him: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it was, ſhee came not empty. Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heereby the practiſe of many profeſſours in the world, who loue to come to Chriſt of free coſt: if hee once proue chargeable, they will ſhrinke in the wetting: and their profeſſion growes cold when coſt is required: but let vs walke with theſe Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies into the Phariſies houſe, and ſee how
<hi>Mary</hi> there behaued her ſelfe. Firſt, we find her ſtanding at Chriſts feet behinde him: for as the Publican durſt not lift his eyes to heauen, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. ſo was <hi>Mary</hi> aſhamed to behold her Sauiour in the face, ſhee goeth boldly into the houſe: ſhee feareth not the countenance of thoſe that were preſent: ſhee knew whom ſhee had offended, and therefore in an humble baſhfulneſſe ſhee caſt her ſelfe behind him: <hi>Againſt thee O Lord haue I ſinned</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Dauid</hi> in his 51. Pſalme:) Why doth <hi>Dauid</hi> ſay ſo? Had he not tranſgreſſed againſt <hi>Vriah</hi> alſo? It is as much as if
<hi>Dauid</hi> had ſaide: Though I haue ſinned diuers wayes, and offended others, yet it is thou (O Lord alone) which cauſeſt me to be aſhamed of my ſin. Thus was <hi>Mary</hi> affected when ſhe came into the houſe, her ſinnes againſt Chriſt made her abaſhed to looke vpon him. This is flatly contrary to the practiſe of worldly men and women, who neuer care how groſſely they offend their God, ſo the dores be ſhut, &amp; they can eſcape the ſhame of men:<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12976:26"/>as for Chriſt, they will ſtare him in the face: his eies they feare not, ſo the world do not ſee them: if they can be drunke in a cellar: if they can oppreſſe cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly with ſome pretty colour: if they can but get the good opinion of men: as for Chriſt Ieſus they will beard him to his head, and braue him out of countenance. This holy conuert was otherwiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: ſhe was not aſhamed becauſe of the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie:</hi> the gueſts which were at the bord did not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright her; the multitude in the houſe, nothing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her: It was only Chriſts preſence that ſtrucke her conſcience, and therfore ſhe ſtood behind him. But what did ſhe there? I will tell you but of one thing ſhe did, and leaue the reſt to your reading in the Text. She beganne to water his feet with her teares: that is ſuch a fountaine of teares guſhed out of her eyes, as that they beganne to water Chriſts feet, (not onely wet them) and that as ſhe ſtood al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, before ſhe bowed herſelfe vnto the ground, to wipe them, to kiſſe them, to annoynt them with her oyntment. O what a wonderfull griefe did this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man conceiue for her ſinfull life paſt: that being a woman (no doubt) of ſome reaſonable ſtature (for <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> is held to haue beene a comely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) yet euen as ſhee ſtood, did her teares runne downe her cheekes: did they deſcend to the ground and watered the feet of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Surely, that ſame ice which was congealed in her breaſt, being frozen in her ſinnes: did now at her comming to Chriſt, reſolue and flowed from her eyes. She ſet her ſinnes in the eyes of her minde, and her ſinnes ſet teares in the eyes of her bodie.<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12976:26"/>Let vs learne to follow <hi>Mary</hi> in this godly practiſe. If <hi>Baronius</hi> (out of his old manuſcript) ſayth true, ſhe came with <hi>Lazarus</hi> and her ſiſter <hi>Martha</hi> into <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine:</hi> Her example is thereby made more proper vnto vs. Wherefore let vs with <hi>Mary</hi> ſet our ſinnes before vs, that our eyes may weepe for vs. Nettles and thornes are hurtfull in a garden; yet are they profitable in the pale or hedge: for that they ſerue as a fence to preſerue the ſame. Sinnes in the ſoule are very dangerous vnto it, they pricke, they ſting, they wound the conſcience like nettles and thornes but retaine them in the memory: keepe them in the skirt of the ſoule, that thou mayſt mourne for them, and then are they profitable to defend the ſoule. <hi>Adam</hi> was placed ouer againſt
<hi>Paradice. Gen.</hi> 3. that beholding the garden from whence hee was caſt and therby being brought to the remembrance of his ſinne he might be grieued for it. So <hi>Marie</hi> heere recounting with her ſelfe; that ſhee had loſt her God, and the pleaſures of <hi>Paradice</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of her fleſh, ſhe is grieued at the heart, and reſolued into teares. Often haue I ſeene the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens to raine vpon the earth, but neuer the <hi>earth to poure ſhowers</hi> vpon <hi>heauen</hi> till now: here is an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly woman, which watereth heauenly feet. <hi>Peter</hi> went out and wept bitterly: but heere is one that bluſheth not to weepe within dores, at a feaſt: and where is wont to bemirth; ſhe fals a monrning. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed God commanded
<hi>Numbers</hi> 29. <hi>in maxima ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitate, in the greateſt feast,</hi> to offer vp a Goat for a ſacrifice for ſinne: There is no time of ioy no <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne aſſembly:</hi> wherein the remembrance of our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12976:27"/>ſinnes is not grateful vnto God, if thou ſigheſt before thou eateſt: if thou chance to weepe for thy ſins at a feaſt, thy teares are accepted. Chriſt in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honor that was euer giuen vnto him in this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life, when multitudes came from Ieruſalem, &amp; receiued him triumphantly, with great boughes and ſongs of ioy: then did he mourne in all that pompe for the ſinnes of Ieruſalem. And this holy woman knew that at this banquet, plenty of teares would bee more gratefull and ioyfull vnto Chriſt then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bowles of Wine. Wee doe not reade that ſhe ſpake as ſhee wept: No, no, ſhee ſtoode as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man confounded in herſelfe: <hi>Non legimus quae dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, ſed legimus quae fecit, vt intelligamus, apud Deum plus valere opera quam verba:</hi> We reade what ſhee did: not what ſhee ſaid, to let vs know, that works are auailable with God more then words. And vnto whom ſhall I haue a regard (ſaith God) but to one that is contrite, broken hearted, and who trembleth at my ſayings?
<hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake not a word, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. And yet ſayeth God vnto <hi>Moſes; Why doeſt thou cry vnto me?</hi> Such was the griefe of
<hi>Mary,</hi> her teares, her ſighes, her ſobs did ſtop her mouth, onely in her heart ſhee cried and ſpake as <hi>Moſes</hi> did. Wee may not neglect this holy example, hauing a cloude of Motiues calling vpon vs to follow her ſteppes. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>
               </label>(<hi>One</hi>) taken from our vocation. wher unto God hath called vs. In the 22. of <hi>Eſay</hi> the 12. verſe. The Lord of hoſtes is ſaid to call vs vnto weeping and mourning: In the 2. of <hi>Ioel</hi> the 17. verſe: <hi>Let the Prieſts</hi> (ſaith God)
<hi>and the Miniſters of the Lord weepe between the Porch and the Altar.</hi> And it is Saint <hi>Paules</hi> iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12976:27"/>1.
<hi>Corinth.</hi> 7.17. that as God hath called euery man, ſo he ſhould walke. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Another Motiue:</hi> is from the prediction of Chriſt: who in the 16. of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 20. <hi>verſe</hi> foretold, that his Church ſhould weepe. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay vnto you, yee ſhall lament, and weepe, and the world ſhall reioyce. Weeping</hi> is the
<hi>badge</hi> of the <hi>Church: Laughing</hi> of <hi>worldly men.</hi> All the Saints of God haue beene deep ſighers, great weepers. King <hi>Dauid</hi> thought it no diſparagement for him to ſay, that hee cauſed his <hi>bed to ſwimme, and watered his couch with teares. Pſalm.</hi> 6. 6.
<hi>verſe. Hezekias</hi> a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble King wept very ſore 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 20.
3. <hi>verſe. Iob</hi> in his 30. chap. 25. <hi>verſe,</hi> appealeth vnto God in this caſe. <hi>Did not I weepe with him that was in trouble, and was not my ſoule in heauineſſe for the poore? Eſay</hi> the Prophet in his
22. chapter 4. <hi>verſe,</hi> wept and would not be comforted.
<hi>Ieremy</hi> in his 9. <hi>chapter</hi> 1. <hi>verſe, Wiſheth that his head were full of water, and his eyes a fountaine of teares, that he might weepe day and night. Daniel</hi> was <hi>in heauineſſe for three weekes of daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Dan.</hi> 10.2. The Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter wept bitterly, Matth.</hi> 26. Of all the holy <hi>Kings, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſours, Children of God</hi> it may beeſayd as it is in the 126.
<hi>Pſalme. verſe. Quod ibant flentes, that they all went by weeping croſſe.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>
               </label> A third motiue: may bee taken from the names in the Scriptures which are giuen vnto the faithfull: in the ninth of
<hi>Exechiel</hi> the fourth, they are call <hi>Mourners</hi> and
<hi>Cryers.</hi> In the ſixteenth of <hi>Marc.</hi> the tenth. This our
<hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> who went to tell the Brethren that Chriſt was riſen, is ſayd to goe vnto them who mourned and wept. And if names bee giuen
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12976:28"/>(as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> tels vs) to expreſſe the nature of things: It is then very naturall for faythfull ones to be Mourners and weepers. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>4</label> A fourth motiue may be taken from promiſes made vnto vs, that if wee <hi>mourne we ſhall be comforted.</hi> In the 61. <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Eſay</hi> the 12. <hi>verſe.</hi> Chriſt is ſayd to be ſent to preach good tidings vnto the poore, <hi>to binde vp the broken hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to comfort thoſe that mourne.</hi> To giue vnto them
<hi>Beauty</hi> for <hi>Aſhes,</hi> the garment of <hi>gladneſſe,</hi> for the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>heauineſſe.</hi> Who would not bee a
<hi>Mourner</hi> when as Chriſt onely commeth to cheere vp ſuch a one? will not <hi>promiſes perſwade?</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>5</label> Let then in the fift place, <hi>Iudgements preuaile,</hi> to wring teares from our eyes. For woe ſayth our Sauiour Chriſt <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 28. <hi>verſe,</hi> vnto you which laugh, that is vnto you which liue at eaſe, merily, after the pleaſures of the fleſh, for you ſhall <hi>waile;</hi> ſhew <hi>outward ſignes of heauineſſe,</hi> and <hi>weepe,</hi> and be <hi>inwardly tormented.</hi> After a great feaſt followeth a great paiment, and much laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is recompenced with much woe. If we did but conſider well what howling and gnaſhing of teeth, is prepared in hell for lowde laughers in this world, it would make vs to mourne like <hi>Pellicans</hi> in the
<hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,</hi> like owles in the Deſert, to weepe till our bones were vexed: till our eyes did ſincke, till our hearts were ſmitten within vs, and withered vp like graſſe, as the Prophet ſpeaketh.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>6</label> A ſixt Motiue, may we take from the cauſes of weeping. Within vs, without vs, round about vs. <hi>Quocung, oculot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertis cauſa eſt lachrimarum.</hi> Looke vpon our ſelues, and in our ſelues, vpon our <hi>ignorance, our little deſire to learns, our reiecting of knowledge: our crookedneſſe</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:12976:28"/>
               <hi>in our willes, our corruptions in affections, our Rebellion</hi> againſt God: our want of
<hi>Loue</hi> to our Neighbours, our manifold ſinnes which hang vpon all our
<hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> we ſhall finde in our ſelues great cauſe of wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. There are more ſinnes committed with the little eye of a man, then the teares of all eyes, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the merits of Chriſt) can euer waſh away. Look vpon others, and in others, vpon thoſe horrible wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes that are committed by them, vppon the prophaning of the Sabaoth: vpon the common vſe of ſwearing: the beaſtly ſinne of whoring, the ſwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſinne of drinking, the default of Magiſtrates in puniſhing, and there will appeare vnto a religious heart infinite cauſe of weeping. If there were wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting weeping worke at home, there were enough abroad. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>7</label> Seuenthly the place wherein wee liue ſhould mooue vs heereunto:
<hi>Wiſdome</hi> doth teach vs to ſquare and apply our ſelues vnto that place wherein we are conuerſant: A Courtier muſt not behaue himſelfe like a Country man, nor a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try man like a Courtier. If beeing at a funerall or in the houſe of mourning we ſhould doe nothing elſe but laugh, all would wonder at vs, for ſo ſtrange a behauiour. The place wherein wee are it is the world: reſembled vnto the ſea, full of dangers, of rockes, or rempeſts. Our bodies which are the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to carry vs in this ſea, are weake, crazy, ſo many ſences, ſo many leakes to let dangers in.
<hi>Rimarum pleni ſumus,</hi> we are full of Rifts. In a word
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in a vale of miſeries, in a vally of teares, and ſighes, and teares doe beſt becomme vs in such a place. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">motive </seg>8</label> A laſt motiue may bee draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> from the nature of <pb n="52" facs="tcp:12976:29"/>
               <hi>Conuerſion.</hi> Thou art a continuall ſinner, yet deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to bee ſaued: thou muſt then continually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new thy repentance. He that repenteth muſt turne vnto his God, and <hi>Ioel</hi> telles vs in his ſecond chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 12. <hi>verſe,</hi> that it muſt be done with all the heart, with faſting, with weeping and with mourning. Thus did <hi>Dauid</hi> turne vnto his God. <hi>Lord</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>Pſalme</hi> 38. <hi>I poure out my whole deſire before thee, and my ſighing is not hid from thee, my heart pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: my ſtrength fasleth: I am bowed and crooked very ſore: I goe mourning all the day long:</hi> will wee then turne vnto our God: Repent vs of our ſinnes and be ſaued: wee muſt roare with <hi>Dauid</hi> for very griefe of heart: mourne with <hi>Magdalen.</hi> Chriſt wept for the ſinnes of others: It were a ſhame then for vs, not to weepe for our owne tranſgreſſions. Haue we liued in ſinne, which cauſed Chriſt, not onely to ſhed teares, but to ſpend his bloud for vs: and did there neuer yet falle a teare from our owne eyes? Haue we liued 20. 40. 80. yeeres, and can we not remember that wee euer wept for our ſinnes? A ſhrewd ſigne that we neuer yet repented. Teares for ſin (ſayth S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) are like the water which Chriſt turned into wine: they are like <hi>Noahs</hi> floud which doe waſh and clenſe as they goe: <hi>Oratio De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um lenit, ſed lachryma cogit, illa vngit haec pungit</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Hierome</hi>). <hi>It is a dry ſacrifice</hi> (ſayth <hi>Gregory</hi>) <hi>that is not watered with teares.</hi> Is it childiſhneſſe to weepe? if it were ſo we muſt be like children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee enter into the Kingdome of Heauen. Wherefore, ſeeing we are called vnto mourning: ſeeing Chriſt foretold that we ſhould be weepers, <pb n="53" facs="tcp:12976:29"/>ſeeing wee are ſo called in the Scriptures: ſeeing there are great rewards for weepers: great puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for laughers: ſeeing there are many cauſes to mourne, within vs, without vs, round about vs: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world is a place of teares; and that our
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion</hi> muſt be ioyned with a ſadneſſe of heart: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo many Motiues to perſwade: Let not <hi>Maries</hi> example be ſlightly regarded: whoſe heart &amp; eyes were relatiues in ſorrow: A ſtagge if he be compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with dogges, will weepe and mourne: Hath an vnreaſonable creature ſuch an impreſſion of griefe becauſe of his enemies? much more then ought men and women ſhed teares: being compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with ſo many Diuels, ſo many euils: ſet vpon with <hi>fiends:</hi> burthened with ſinnes peſtred with a thouſand infirmities: wherefore let vs drowne our ſinnes with the teares of our eyes, as the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were drowned with the waters of the ſea. Let vs ſay with <hi>Dauid, my teares, haue beene my meat day and night,</hi> let vs ſay with Chriſt, <hi>my Soule is heauie:</hi> let vs open the fountaines of our eyes with <hi>Marie</hi> and ſtrangle our ſinnes with the ſtreames of our teares: for ſhe ſtood at Chriſts feet behinde him weeping and beganne to waſh his feete with her teares, you may finde further in the Text, that ſhee did wipe them with the haires of her head, that ſhe kiſſed his feete, and annoynted them with her oyntment. <hi>Quot habuit in ſe oblectamenta, tot fecit de ſe holocau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta,</hi> her eyes, her haires, her lips, her oyntment all the inſtruments of her death, were turned at her <hi>Conuerſion</hi> into the means of life. God giue vs grace to embrace her example. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
